good evening everyone we're going to get started i now call to order the city council the special meeting of city council finance committee for november 18th 2025 good evening everyone please take a moment to silence your phones and devices if you haven't done so already tonight we have a special meeting of the finance committee there's no general public comment during this meeting but after each department presentation the finance committee chair will open the floor first for council comments and then public comment duration of public comment is limited to three
minutes per speaker please begin with your name and block of residence for our meeting record and to keep time i'll use the light in front of me it will turn green when three minutes begins it will blink yellow when there's one minute remaining and it will blink red when three
minutes has been expended thank you in advance for ensuring equal time for all our first order of the business tonight is approving the minutes of the city council finance committee meeting of october 21st 2025. motion to approve second we have a motion and a second counselors any comments on those minutes you've been provided with hearing now mr harris uh madam president before we proceed with that i'm so sorry uh we should have a roll call of members thank you i forgot to do that let's begin with the roll call of members and then we'll pick up where we left off mr. med here mr. Roya here mr. Cleese yeah miss Craig miss Diaz mr. Hirsch here I'm president big a here Thank You counselors Diaz and Craig are excused this evening okay back to where we were we had a motion and a second there was no council comments in the minutes just making sure that that's still true mr. Harris if you would Thank You madam president mr. men ah mr. Roya
Oh, I mr. Cleese. All right, mr. Hirsch. All right, I'm president Baker. Hi Thank you as always for keeping me straight
All right, and with that I'll turn it over to councillor Arroyo with the Finance Committee meeting. Thank you council president
I'll open the Finance Committee. Thank you everyone for joining us this evening for day two of the budget hearing We'll have presentations from the neighborhood department neighborhood engagement offices office of the mayor office of the solicitor City Council and controller
and then the Department of Public Works works I'll invite director Tina Campbell to give us a budget update and overview all right so I am gonna give an overview but first I wanted to give just a brief update again of where we are in
the schedule perfect all right thank you thank you if the clicker doesn't work
works thank you all right um so this is the the second budget hearing as as you just heard and you will be hearing tonight from the department from the departments listed here so neighborhood engagement mayor's office solicitor's office elected officials and Public Works which includes the utility funds and additionally tonight I am gonna start with some updates we've actually made a number of adjustments to the general fund and the water fund budgets based on both feedback from you and further work within the city administration and I will also respond at the end of my overview here to questions that have been posted on engage Lancaster up to this point so just a reminder next week is the first reading of the budget ordinance and December 9th will be the second reading and that's when the vote on the ordinance will will happen and then there's a final opportunity to answer any questions that come from engage Lancaster at our committee meeting on December 1st so just a top-line recap as I mentioned we've made a number of changes to the draft of the budget that we're now recommending and we have actually posted those changes online and they were sent to you counselors last week as well these changes have occurred in the general fund and the water fund and I'm gonna take the remainder of my overview
to talk mainly about the water fund which has prompted the need for many of these changes and then I'm going to outline the recommended changes in both
the water and general fund so we've not made changes in sewer solid waste and recycling or stormwater funds so those are those budgets remain as they were on October 6th when we introduced the budget on October 6 we did not recommend any tax or utility increases for city residents and with our proposed changes that you'll hear about tonight this still remains true we're not proposing
any tax increases or utility fee increases for city residents as we mentioned in the October meetings we are currently undergoing a PUC rate case
request in water so we do anticipate a rate increase for outside city water customers sometime in 2026 all right so last week council received a memo from
director Stephen Campbell and myself pertaining to the water fund and the
general fund and I'm gonna provide a summary of that memo for the benefit of the public this evening so as an overview the water utility managed by the City of Lancaster through the Department of Public Works provides services for the city as well as nine surrounding municipalities about 30% of the customers of the water fund are inside the city limits and about 70% of
the customers are outside of the city limits in order to provide essential
clean water for our customers, the water fund bears the weight of some significant financial obligations. And these obligations include ensuring that the vast amounts of infrastructure
needed for the utility are performing properly. It includes ever-changing and often unfunded
regulated compliance and an annual inter-fund equity transfer to the general fund. As a result, THE WATER FUND CURRENTLY CARRIES 55% OF THE TOTAL DEBT OF THE ENTIRE CITY BUDGET, SO ACROSS ALL OF THE FUNDS. THIS RESULTS IN DEBT SERVICE PAYMENTS COMPRISING ABOUT 36% OF THE WATER FUND'S ANNUAL BUDGET. AND WITH THE MAJOR NEEDS OF OUR AGING INFRASTRUCTURE AND UPCOMING UNFUNDED MANDATES, WE'RE PROJECTING
MORE BORROWING IN THE APPROVED CAPITAL PLAN, WHICH INCLUDES THE WATER MAIN TRANSMISSION
line replacement that you've been hearing about. In 2022, PFM, who's worked with us on various financial analyses over the years, conducted an evaluation of our water system. They found that we have an operationally sound system, which means that we've been making the necessary improvements in the system to ensure that it is running well. And it means that we're running the operations efficiently. If you factor out debt payments and some of the chemical costs, our operation expenses grew by three percent year over year between 2021 and 2024. again this is factoring out debt so while our rates are considered affordable that affordability is threatened by high debt requirements which result in a weak financial position basically meaning that there isn't room in the water fund budget to work towards a healthy cash reserve over the last several weeks we've been working to reduce expenses in the water fund so as you may have seen in the proposed budget initially the 2026 proposed budget contemplated a deficit of 5.6 million the 2025 approved water budget includes a 3 million dollar deficit and the 2025 budget was approximately 20 higher than 2024. we are projecting that we will be under budget and expenses for 2025 but it has still resulted resulted in a higher year-over-year increase than the previous years this is in large part due to three factors it's an increase in the debt expenses because of our previous debt amortization schedules it's an increase in the general fund transfer which I'll talk about more on the next slide and an increase in the operating costs such as chemicals as well as as medical insurance which you've heard me talk about often the 20% increase is not a result of increased staffing but rather these these costs that you see here and additionally in 2025 we're seeing a slight decline in revenues because we are seeing a decrease in consumption so decreasing consumption is ultimately good we have in fact been encouraging this through the recent drought but this still means that our revenue might not come in as anticipated in 2025 so part of the increase in 2025 budget was an increase in the annual transfer from the water fund to the general fund this transfer has been in the budget for over two decades since moving the water fund from a municipal authority into the regular operations of the city the transfer is an owner's equity transfer and it's helped the general fund but has continued to fuel the weak position financial position of the water fund and in our original proposal for 2026 budget we have proposed a 3.6 million dollar transfer so just a note in the past few years the city has started to take steps to address the weak financial position in the water fund in 23 and 24 the administration reduced the transfer to two million dollars annually it was at four million dollars annually and this was possible because we received arpa funds that we could use as revenue replacement in the general starting in 2021 the administration refinanced some debt in order to see a savings in the water fund of about 2.6 million the city has been increasing fees we increased fees in 2020 2022 and 2023 for inside city customers and we did a puc rate increase for outside city customers in 22 and as i mentioned we're currently in another puc rate case and anticipate that for outside city customers in mid 2026. um and we've continued to try to keep the water fund running as lean as possible not allowing the fund to grow more than the rate of inflation if you take out debt as i mentioned earlier i'll say this is a huge accomplishment for the water utility as we've seen the cost of goods needed for operations continue to increase and in recent years we've also needed to continue to borrow funds for infrastructure needs so since 2022 we've needed to borrow about 42 million for major projects and you see some of those major projects listed as well as many small needs the projects listed here are also part of the capital improvement plan that
was approved if they haven't already been completed some of them have been completed
additionally we've seen a number of regulatory and operational pressures that are causing more increases in 2026. so our lead line replacement work and pfos work are unfunded regulated require regulatory requirements and we are now starting to see some significant spending in these areas moving forward we're seeing an increased system flushing requirement which is also causing an increase in costs and we were locked into a great electric rate through the end of this year through the end of 2025 but that contract needed to be bid again and resulted in an increase of almost 60 percent which translates to about 750 000 in the budget while the administration has been attempting to address the cash position of the water we also have had a couple of historic barriers that needed to be addressed that now have been so the approval of the home rule charter last year has been very important in providing flexibility for the general fund to allow
that fund to not be so completely reliant on the revenue transfer from the water fund
and we needed a clearer picture of the long-term capital budget i know it seems like every time
i'm in front of you i talk about how amazing it is that we actually have a capital budget now
but it is truly an enormous help in our forecasting and understanding of what of what is needed for long-term projections so for 2026 we are recommending a number of adjustments to both the water fund and the general fund as i have said there are other recommendations in the memo that we provided to council but i'm only going to focus on two key recommendations tonight for the water fund so first we are recommending that we eliminate the 3.6 million dollar transfer to the general fund that we initially proposed this will mean some adjustments to the general fund and i'll address those next second we're recommending that a task force be established to do long-term planning for the water fund this task force should be created immediately upon the transition to a new administration so that we can start to plan for 2027 and beyond so to the general fund eliminating the three point six million dollar transfer to this fund means that we need to reduce expenses in the general fund we've reduced some small line items and those are included in the budget that's posted online but the main adjustments are listed here so we have eliminated one of the new positions and are not filling six others that are currently vacant or this is the
proposal we've kept in some new positions because the analysis have shown that they either generate revenue or save costs that are beyond the
expenses we've done some adjustments in our fleet share to slow replacements of
a couple of the vehicles and work in-house with our mechanics to ensure
that we do the improvements needed on the on the fleet as well we've slowed down the replacement of some of the street lights to LED lights and we've reduced some of our funding for design work which could result in some adjustments to the timeline for the capital projects but that will be reflected in next year's capital budget in addition to these expense eliminations we are also proposing that we pay off approximately four point one million in the final principal left to be paid on the 2007 bond so we're
proposing that we use data center permit revenues for this which will provide an annual savings of 1.5 million each year for the next three years it will also
eliminate about four hundred and twenty four thousand in interest payments we are also proposing that we use approximately two hundred ninety thousand from the permitting fees the data center permitting fees to cover
permit positions related to improving the permitting process that we discussed
at the first budget hearing on October 21st this is in addition to the three 390,000 that we were projecting in staff time directly related to the permit work for the data centers There are also other expenses that will be incurred for the data centers And I'll provide be providing an update of those estimates for 2026 costs to you next week We do anticipate that we would still have a surplus from these data center fees after these expenses and the payoff in the previous slide and finally we are recommending that we use some cash reserves so we had initially proposed using approximately 1 million in cash reserves we're now proposing using a bit more 1.5 million which still will ensure that we're at the high end of the recommendation for cash reserves in the general fund this is possible because we're projecting to be under our expenses in 2025 which will result in over 4 million dollars going into the cash reserve in 2025. just a couple more slides um so because i mentioned the home rule charter earlier i wanted to just show a bit of before and after so even though home rule even though having home rule doesn't mean that we won't need to continue to work very hard to contain costs we are in a much better position now than we were last year so this is the before home rule projections using the 2025 and 2026 assumptions that we were including last year before we knew if we were getting home rule what we changed in this from last year was to assume no real estate or earned income tax increases this assumes no increases and we've taken out the water fund equity transfer for the whole time for 2026 and further so as i've said with this chart before please focus on the bottom two lines the fund balance is our cash reserves and then the the fund balance percent is the that percentage that I've been talking about between 15 and 20. so if you notice on here we would run out of fund balance next year so we would have one year before we ran out of cash reserves in this scenario without some sort of intervention obviously and these are the projections based on our current scenario so one thing that I do want to note you'll note that the projections in this slide for 2026 are not the same as on the last slide this is because
we would have had to adjust a number of things in 2026 without home rule so that's why the
projections look different we're using the projections in the previous slide that we that we would have anticipated last year so again before we knew if we were working with home rule or not the projections on this on this slide show a lot of assumptions of expense grows that we feel we can actually negotiate in the future and this assumes that we would never again have an equity transfer from the water fund which wouldn't necessarily be the case based on recommendations from the water task force that will be created this is different from what we presented on October 6th again since it would have included the water fund transfer this also assumes no increase in either tax. So if you look at the bottom two lines in this slide, you can see that the fund balance remains stronger for much longer. It doesn't mean that we don't have work to do to contain and decrease costs. We said often last year that home rule was the best option that we
had, but it wasn't a magic wand. However, home rule has definitely given us more options for
the work and allowed us to continue to focus on how we ensure cost savings and efficiency in the future to avoid tax increases. So as we look ahead, we are working already, so work's already underway to contain and eliminate costs. So we're currently working on deployment of solar to take advantage of some tax credits that will expire in July. If we get this implemented, we will actually see costs in our electric, or we will see cost savings in our electric already in 2027, which be a huge help since I mentioned that those have been going up we've I've already been talking
about that we'll be intensely focused on health care cost savings in 2026 and we're working on
continued options for debt elimination in the general fund in the future and as I mentioned
in my October 21st presentation we've spent money over the past three years on implementation of new
technology and that's coming online or already is online and that will help us to be more efficient and doing our work in the future as well so finally tonight i'll just quickly shift gears and answer some of the questions that are the questions that have come in on engage lancaster so there's been seven questions and i will summarize them i'm not going to get into
quite all of the details that we will post online but those will be posted online
after the after the meeting this evening so the first one was related to actually the WONDERING IF WE COULD SUPPORT PUBLIC SCHOOLS UNTIL THE STATE BUDGET HAD PASSED. SO WE'RE GRATEFUL THAT THE STATE BUDGET HAS PASSED, AND WE ARE HOPEFUL THAT THE SCHOOL DISTRICT IS GETTING THE ACCESS TO THE FUNDING THAT THEY NEED. THE SECOND ONE WAS AROUND, IT WAS A MULTI-QUESTION AROUND RESERVE FUNDS. SO HAVE WE USED RESERVE FUNDS IN RECENT YEARS TO FILL A REVENUE GAP? they're concerned that we will need to draw from reserve funds continuing and what amount or percentage of the budget is best practice for municipalities to keep in a reserve fund so i mentioned already between 15 and 20 percent is healthy and in recent years we we have budgeted to use the reserve fund to fill revenue gaps but we haven't actually had to use it because of the administration's commitment to keeping expenses low there was a question around when the general fund debt servicing may start to decrease and as i mentioned we're actually proposing paying off some of that in 2026 beyond this proposal the debt service in the general fund would start to decrease in 2030 assuming that no additional debt is is added and then there were
some questions around options available for pennsylvania cities to level out medical and
pension expenses. This is a bit more of a complicated answer as this is a problem that persists across every industry in the United States and government entities are affected in similar ways. I will say that in 2015 the city decided to become self-insured which really has saved the city millions of dollars in the past decade. We will continue to see increases but
But our self-insured status does keep us – keep the increases lower than the national average. So in 2026, the average annual increase for medical expenses is actually expected to be
about 26 percent, and we are projecting around 5 percent because we're self-insured. And I think pension costs will also continue to rise.
We're seeing some decrease in the actual pension expenses, but because of state contributions
to the pension funds unfortunately that that might not even out for us um there was a question around how additional staff is the best solution to providing services to the residents i mentioned
this briefly but some of the increased staff is a result of analysis which shows that hiring staff
was less expensive than continuing to contract out the services that we needed we're also trying to work to prioritize the needs of the community that we've been hearing like an updated permitting process as we've discussed there was a question regarding seeing the full capital plan so we will make sure that link is posted but that is also on our budget page online and then finally there was a question related to the animal shelter expenses in the police bureau line and so i just wanted to say most of the expenses for the for the building that houses the animal shelter are actually included either in the public works department or in the capital budget plan um but because the
animal shelter specifically supports the police work with stray dogs some of the maintenance
related to that work is included in the police bureau and we didn't anticipate that there would be quite as many expenses in that line so that was cut that was one of the pieces of the question as
well so it was cut a little bit in the budget this year i will stop there thank you director campbell um i will open it up for council for any questions or comments council president thank you uh director
campbell thank you very much and the memo that you provided to council laying this out ahead of time was extremely helpful i wanted to go back to that second projection slide and just to be clear about what is projected on there and what isn't projected on there so you mentioned um it assumes no owner's equity transfer from the water fund over time you mentioned it assumes no adjustment to tax rate does it include the forecasted growth of earned
income tax over time it does include that okay so that's dialed into that projection okay thank you
thank you council president counselor med uh thank you mr vice president thank you uh director Campbell. My question is given that there was a structural deficit in the general fund even after home rule I appreciate the projections. I do have some concerns about like the sustainability of the elimination of the transfers from the water fund to the general fund. Would you be able to talk about that a little bit? I understand there's going to be a task force but I mean what is this to do to future projections down the line yeah so this is the what what is showing on the screen is projecting it without any transfer so this is sort of what the the future would be without any transfer i don't i i wouldn't say that that it's the city's administration that the city administration's recommendation that we continue that i think it's simply something that needs to
be looked at so I don't I I don't want to say that we're suggesting that that is going to be eliminated forever in the future but it's just something that
needs to be needs to be worked with and thank you and also my other question was what the 2007 bond paying that off do we not have the debt service to take on do
we not have the capacity to take on the debt service the next several years years without paying that off and using some of those revenues in other places and could those revenues be used as like revenue replacement from the data
centers rather than paying off the loan yes the answer to that question is yes you could use it as a revenue replacement but you would only get one year versus this would get you one at 1.5 million dollars in savings over the next three years and avert four hundred and twenty four thousand dollars of interest payments so it's it's well positioned as we only have I mean it's almost paid off but there are as you're looking at some of the outstanding debt that has been refinanced that has included some larger payments at the end and so by paying off early you're saving more money rather than doing revenue replacement which is a one-time thing and if we didn't pay it off we'd be looking at a negative one point five starting in 2026 correct yeah that's so this these projections are including paying that off so 26 27 and 28 would see an additional 1.5 in expenses thank you that concludes my questions Thank You councillor met actually I'm gonna piggyback off of your first question just for the sake of clarity so director Campbell when we were doing the four million dollar transfer from the water fund that was regardless if the water utility was producing a surplus or deficit we were taking that owner's equity and subsidizing our general fund what could happen in the future is with the elimination of this transfer is once the water utility is maybe one day providing a surplus we can then use the surplus from the water fund to help support operations in the general fund that explained well yes and if I could just narrate that just add just a little bit more to that what it this is taking a step to invest in an asset that the city owns that can be a revenue producer long into the future and it is prudent to do so in this way rather in my opinion rather than to continue the transfer and continue to erode the financial position of the water fund to the detriment of the city water payer rate payers for water because those are the ones that do not require PUC oversight and I think to I mean the the other the other piece of this is that as we think about this this transfer the the water fund as I mentioned has been running very efficiently kudos to the team I don't know if everybody's here but they they've been doing a great job of running it efficiently but have never been able to build up a healthy cash reserve because of this transfer to the
general fund so if we have that there's also a little bit more flexibility with the water fund as well great Thank You councillor Hirsch Thank You council vice president thank you director Campbell for the presentation my
question is around the areas of focus for cost savings that you mentioned so deployment health care focusing on cutting costs their debt elimination and the deployment of you know technologies that might save us cost over the long
term my question is just is there any sense of what those savings are going to mean year over year and then in the long run of this projection that we're
looking at here and I know that I'm sure a lot of that is kind of nebulous like
it's hard to know exactly what savings will come from like some of these investments that we're making but is there any general sense because I think as we're looking at this projection and we're thinking about to what extent do
we balance strengthening the position of the water fund by reducing the transfer from there to the general fund versus this picture here where we would you know see deficits in the future yeah I mean I don't have numbers with me tonight I will say we have not included these cost savings in these projections that's correct so we haven't included any cost savings at this point in these
projections so that's a piece that definitely we would be we would be
looking at solar deployment we have some pretty clear numbers on already the rest of it is a little bit more nebulous but we're working on on some of that as well so and I'll just add that in the analysis related to the debt priority payoffs after the 2007 refinance if council were to approve that at four point one million there's a 2009 refinance at four point five million that would generate one point two million dollars in savings over four years as a the next priority payment taking into consideration the the total interest savings that the time frame and the amount of savings so prioritizing
savings first and so in addition to 1.2 million dollars annually it would be averting six hundred and twenty five thousand dollars in interest payments so
again that's just that's an example if you were to to pay off additional debt using the data center as a as a means to right-size that that would have direct and immediate impact on the general fund for four years that's that's helpful because I think what I'm thinking about this like and I understand not having an
exact number at this moment again this is a lot there's a lot that goes into
this and and we're looking down the road I guess I'm trying to get a general sense of like I'm looking at I am just trying to get a general sense of like our
cost savings going to be you know ten million dollars over the next ten years is it gonna be 20 is it gonna be 30 I don't know I'm not sure that I could say it would be 30 million over the next 10 years be quite impressive but the reason
I guess I'm asking that question is just because I'm looking at you know 2035 we're saying the fund balance would be negative 54 and again, this is assuming no water transfer This is assuming, you know, none of these cost savings that we would realize it might be conservatively estimating Revenue growth or other expense reductions, but so like I'm trying to figure out how we get that 54 You just putting big round numbers in my head like to closer to where we want that operating reserve to be if expenses are almost 100 million
dollars that year you'd want it to be somewhere in the ballpark of 15 to 20 million so how do we get 70 million dollars over the next 10 years outside of the assumptions that are baked into
this chart is kind of the question I'm going towards and I know there's a lot that has to be sorted out in that question but i don't know if that makes a little more sense for why i'm asking like what can we expect to see in cost savings yeah it does make sense i think that the other thing to think about with these projections is so i'm not sure that i'm really going to answer your question but as we look at it um this is this is assuming that we're going to start spending uh we're going to start needing you know basically to take out a loan in 2029 because we're going to run out of uh reserve funds if we in 2027 don't have a deficit of 5.6 million that you know kind of exponentially helps that um that fund balance it's a cumulative impact right and so the next the the i appreciate you're looking at that big number at the end but i draw your attention back to 2027 and the planning for that because you start eliminating those deficits and then you you forego the cumulative impact that gets you out to that really big number at the end yes has been the story forever it's just that we're we're stronger than we have been but we need to get the water fund in a better stronger position because then if you if you start adding back in transfers from the water fund then you're cumulatively reducing even if it's a two million dollars over time by one two three like by six years seven years at two million that's fourteen
million dollars right there no that's helpful and I mean obviously the further out you go the less concrete these numbers are so it makes sense to be you know focused more short term so thank you
council president thank you to go back to the the equity transfers in the past I think in the past we've done as much as four million dollars was that based on actual performance ever no it was never based on actual performance well I shouldn't say that that we could tell it wasn't based on actual performance but um yeah in the recent years it hasn't been so the the water fund task force that you're proposing could work on ensuring that whatever a transfer would be in the future that could eliminate some of that that we're talking about is actually based on performance of the water fund could be a percentage of profits or that sort of thing or based on cash reserve uh yeah thank you and counselor colleagues oh thank you thank you director campbell for the presentation um you mentioned during the presentations that um there are some measures that the administration has taken in order to reduce expenses we know that it's important to wages expenses don't you think that that's those measures may affect us some of the services provided by the
city and how did the administration decide yeah it's a great question I mean
obviously we're always trying to ensure that we continue to provide you know good service that's needed for residents I think the as we were looking at what
to cut we were looking at ways to maybe slow down the deployment of some of the things that we were doing and not necessarily eliminate it yeah I think that's maybe kind of the broad broad generalization but that's what we were
really trying to look at so for for example in the in the fleet piece we might be slowing down the the you know to kind of turnover of cars which might result in slower savings but will still save us some some money in the future as well so just kind of trying to slow down but not eliminate another question how is the implementation of the budget how will the implementation of the budget be
monitored and are there any reporting mechanisms to ensure transparency and
accountability yeah we provide monthly financial statements now to council and
And then we do a quarterly verbal report here at council meetings as well, so we can continue to do that and reports as requested by council as well. Thank you. No further questions. Thank you. Councilor Med. Thank you. I just had one last question. You mentioned the positions.
Which of the positions weren't being filled or being cut out of the new budget, if there were new positions or ones that weren't being filled that were a part of the changes? the the six the seven positions I don't have the list and I'm not going to remember them all but there are a couple that are currently vacant or will be vacant at the end of the year there's a couple of I believe position cadet positions and police that we didn't think we would be able to fill I can chime in there's there's the deputy chief of staff position will be vacant after next week and that position is being proposed to be held as the new administration comes in and is filling the chief of staff position there is a position related that was the assistant solicitor that position is going to be held open for and and will be further evaluated with the new administration and there's a labor position in parks that is going to be held open economic development program manager was the new position that's been eliminated and that it's just what five and then some reductions in the part-time positions where the cadets we can get you a list so we don't have to fumble through this but that's that's the gist any additional questions or comments from council from the public Randy Grossman 130 North Palm Street in Lancaster just a very quick question why is it that revenues decrease from 2026 to 2027 I'm looking at our data analyst because i actually don't know the answer to that question you know yeah we'll have to look at it and get get back to you controller elect mr grossman thanks for pointing that out hi uh tim stuhlder 800 block of george street um just a couple comments and then a couple questions um uh in terms of comment um this is just disheartening to hear um when the home rule was was passed last year um we were certainly not guaranteed that we would be able to get a full decade without a tax increase but it was strongly implied that absent any unknown or unexpected circumstances we'd have a pretty good shot at it and um you know the water condition of the water fund and the condition of the water infrastructure has been understood for a long time so that should not be an unknown or unexpected situation on a related point in december last year director campbell presented projections showing that in 2030 we would end up with a general fund balance of 17.3 million uh the projections we're seeing now up here 2030 is a negative 12.5 million that is a flip of about 28.5 million that is just a huge flip in in one year
and projections and again i recognize that what we're seeing up here is is a conjecture with a
lot of assumptions it is still a 28.5 million dollar flip in a 60 70 million dollar uh general fund budget in in 12 months um i guess my questions oh and what one more um i guess this is a question for confirmation i recall in previous years director hopkins saying that the reason we make these transfers from the water fund to the general fund is there's an equity component the water fund draws from rate payers outside the city it also draws from large non-taxable properties within the city and that this is a way of getting those folks to pay a little bit more of their fair share and hold city ratepayers a little bit more harmless so i'd ask confirm that that is the case and ask council to consider that as it thinks about these issues and i see my light blinking there so my two questions are
number one how does the um rate case play into these considerations can the city make the case to the puc that look we have this debt we have this infrastructure we have to build we should
be able to ask outside city rate payers to pay a little bit more and then continue this this transfer rather than hit the general fund and second question did i understand correctly that we are planning additional borrowing uh to fund water improvements and uh is the condition of the
water fund affect the interest rates we would get um yeah i i'll uh respond to the first question
first um so the the uh puc actually does not uh recognize the transfer that the equity transfer
that is done so they basically take that out as an expense for the water fund when they are looking
at the rate increase which often means that they do not fund the full amount
that we're requesting because of that so that is it it is a piece that we need to
consider in the in the PUC rate cases did you want to say more on that no keep going I have other things I want to say I'm sorry director Campbell can you say that again like so seeing the four million draw actually hurts our case when asking for an increase with the PUC correct not recognized it's not recognized so it's not recognized as an expense for for the water fund so
basically there's there they're saying that's not they're not going to recognize that it's not sure and I'm already forgetting what the next
question was sorry interesting yes and so yes I mean I think absolutely we have to continue to look at you know the the level of debt because that does affect
interest rate it also affects bond rating which we've been looking at
really closely as well because that then also affects interest rates yeah I think part of this Tim is that yes we have known that the water fund is needed and if you talk to the other director Campbell and he like this has been a sore a source of much consternation this this four million dollar transfer which the four million dollars started with the 27 2018 budget it was the last budget prepared by under the gray administration beginning with my administration we've done revenue replacement for a couple of years we were trying to capitalize some trying to address this in 2023 and 2024 and I
think that there's a couple of things that are more than a couple of things
three things that are really driving some of the concerns elevating the concerns related to the water fund which Tina has talked about but I just want to put up put a finer point on them the drought last year we didn't anticipate that that was gonna drive up our chemical costs significantly we also
didn't anticipate a 1.3 million dollar decline in revenues we need to come up
with and you know have been flummoxed by net metering and the fact that we cannot get we you know solar to our facilities because they're just beyond the what is it Molly three miles two miles of where you can build solar and then get to get to power your own your your own infrastructure so they were there were things that we were working on that did but either didn't pan out or cost increase or revenues declined that have led us to this point it's a pretty
dramatic thing to take three point eight million dollars out of the budget and to
not include any revenue transfers in these projections so I just I caution everybody looking at this to just don't panic because there's a lot of work that can happen over the next 12 months and a lot of which I have full confidence in the next council and the next mayor that they're gonna spend some significant time on this but we couldn't have gotten here without home rule because we would not have been able to forego that again or even for this one year we would not have been able to do that without a property tax increase so I take this as as like a really significant progress actually that we're able to address this yes it looks bad right now for the general fund but that is not a permanent this is not a permanent look at the future it's literally a projection maybe if i can just add i i would say this is a projection but it's the the bleakest of projections like we're not anticipating that this is going to look like this in the next projection that we do based on conversations that need to be had around yeah and in contrast to other units of government in our community we are actually showing you this and talking about the steps that we're taking to reduce and to address this in a strategic and proactive way so there
you have it
Yeah, and if I can just have a 15-second coda do appreciate the challenges the difficulty and the transparency. Thanks Counselor Royale, I'm sorry. Can I just make a very quick statement slash question? So to confirm Mr
Sheldrager's question the projections from last year did include some level of transfer it included four million
So that's that's why the flip. Okay, I can make sure I understood that's where that's where I was going on to make sure I was right and also our rate cases with the PUC are supported by the infrastructure work that we do if my understanding is correct we have to show that we've completed some level of work before we can go back and do them again in my mind that means that we have to make sure that we support that work fully in order to realize increases in the future is that correct that's that's correct yeah so we cannot go to the PUC for any projects that we do until those projects are completed we also have a blackout time so once we get this rate case through we're gonna be blacked out for about two years before before we can go back for another rate case request
okay thank you thank you sorry thank you
mr. president public comment Amos thoughts who is one or block of South
Arch Street I'm thinking back to the last budget hearing and particularly looking or thinking about the police budget um and and i might be wrong about this so you may
have to uh remind me uh so i think in the in the police budget they were trying to get up to the 128 staff members and we're at 110 i think it's about 105 right now 105. so you know i mean and
i also will say like i greatly appreciate these projections i think it allows us to have this conversation uh in a way that we couldn't if you weren't projecting out this for this long so it
is very helpful but i'm wondering why are we not considering uh you know kind of a phased approach to trying to get to that 128 number uh with the police department i i work very closely with the police department i'm in the citizen police academy right now i understand that they're understaffed and that our police department could do a lot more with that full staffing but that is a significant increase and then and those are costs you know when you hire staff and you hire police officers those are costs that are really hard to bring back down if we need to over the next couple years so I'm just curious why the administration
isn't looking at more of a phased approach to getting us up to full
staffing with the police department because our overtime budget is out of control whatever we are over eight hundred thousand dollars we're over a million dollars in overtime and that's not sustainable for our team and the hours that staff have been working i don't think it is particularly good for them individually or their families i don't think it's good to just continue to have an overtime budget that is that extensive yeah so that's helpful but like i mean again couldn't you do a phased approach to try to add some officers decrease overtime sort of over the next couple years rather than trying to do it all at once um i think that a couple of things about that amos and i'd have to go back and
and look so we're gonna have a little bit of a reprieve from retirements but
we're gonna hit like nine retirements I think in two years and so catches catch can because we are gonna we have a really good recruitment class now and
then we're gonna have a little bit of a lull and that's gonna give us time to
get those officers trained and oriented to their new jobs and that takes a year really to get a new police officer fully um positioned within the organization and then
nine retirements so thank you any additional public comment great thank you director campbell um and i will just add you'll you'll hear more about the water fund uh when when director campbell
gives his presentation as well but we're going to shift gears here a little bit great uh we'll now move to the Department of neighborhood engagement good evening it's not a it's
a major shift in conversation yeah just thankful for all the updates that you
shared Tina director Campbell good evening council Milsi Carrasco director of neighborhood engagement for the city of Lancaster really excited to share with you the our department's proposed budget for 2026 and as you know our the work that we're doing touches across all City Hall we have an opportunity to
engage with residents every day as we're walking them welcoming them into City Hall assisting with translation and interpretation services engaging in our
neighborhoods related to our civic engagement programming and celebrating our city's cultures through our tourism special events and neighborhood activation so DJ it's down correct thank you sir and so just a quick framework we We have the Office of Language Services, the Bureau of Civic Engagement, the Bureau of Tourism and Promotions. We have City Hall outside, but City Hall reception actually resides within the Bureau of Civic
Engagement. It's just a different function. So when you look at the budget, reception is also included in the Bureau of Civic Engagement.
So here's a slice of the pie that we have. And our department share of the general fund budget is a little bit less than 2%. OUR IMPACT AS YOU KNOW IS CITYWIDE SO WE REALLY TRY TO MAXIMIZE EVERY DOLLAR THROUGH PARTNERSHIPS GRANTS AS WELL AS TECHNOLOGY AND COLLABORATING WITH DIFFERENT DEPARTMENTS I WANT TO JUST SHARE WITH YOU A LITTLE BIT OF HIGHLIGHTS SO THE OFFICE OF LANGUAGE SERVICES ZIRA'S HERE WITH US THIS EVENING REALLY ENSURES ALL RESIDENTS NO MATTER WHAT LANGUAGE THEY SPEAK can have access to city services information and civic processes without major barriers
some of the highlights for 2025 was we became welcoming recertified which is a very long process and we're really proud of that recertification we are engaging in partner
convenings and engaging partners across city of lancaster related to immigrant and refugee RESETTLEMENT SERVICES AND WE CONDUCTED A LANGUAGE ANALYSIS AND THAT WE'RE STILL WORKING ON AND WE'LL COME BACK TO COUNCIL TO REPORT SOME OF OUR SERVICE STATS AND ZIRA GOES INTO A LITTLE BIT MORE DETAILED DURING WELCOMING WEEK IN SEPTEMBER BUT I JUST WANTED TO HIGHLIGHT WE HAD OVER 121 TRANSLATION INTERPRETATION REQUESTS WE HAD ABOUT 660 PLUS CALLS AND INTERPRETATIONS THAT RESULTED in 26 language requests which are really big numbers and what we're seeing as we shared in
September is the number one department that's utilizing our language services is public safety
so our police officers so we're thankful for that. Our goals in 2026 is to continue to improve on service delivery. We want to make sure we're servicing folks much quicker and the technology THAT WE'RE USING IS MORE EFFICIENT WE WANT TO UPGRADE TECHNOLOGY AS WELL AND DO AN ASSESSMENT
OF THAT WE WANT TO UPDATE THE CITYWIDE LANGUAGE ACCESS POLICY AND REALLY STRENGTHEN THE WORK
WITHIN OUR DEPARTMENTS OOPS I THINK I HIT THAT TWITTER OKAY THE BUREAU OF CIVIC ENGAGEMENT LEADS THE WORK THAT CONNECTS RESIDENTS TO GOVERNMENT EVERY SINGLE DAY AND THROUGH PROGRAMMING AND TECHNOLOGY AS WELL AS STAFF TRAINING AND INTERNAL ENGAGEMENT DEVELOPMENT FOR PROJECT
manager so those are some of the priorities for the bureau of civic engagement i do want to share some stats on our programming so this year alone we um we conducted 43 love your block which is
a record for us we had 43 projects throughout the city of lancaster activating all quadrants of the city and connecting with so many new community leaders josh will be reporting out
JOSH F. BALTREY WHO OVERSEES OUR ENGAGEMENT PROGRAMMING WILL BE COMING TO YOU IN FEBRUARY
AND PROVIDING AN ENGAGEMENT UPDATE WITH MORE DETAILS WE ALSO GRADUATED 43 NEIGHBORHOOD LEADERSHIP ACADEMY WHETHER THEY WERE THROUGH JP MCASKIE OR ADULT PROGRAMS WHICH WE JUST FINALIZED TWO WEEKS AGO AND SOMETHING THAT WE'RE REALLY EXCITED ABOUT AND WE'LL TALK A LITTLE BIT more in future slides is we secured 132 um thousand dollars related to engagement um programming and grants our digital engagement platform which is engaged lancaster and we also utilized it for questions related to our proposed budget we had 13 over 13 000 engaged lancaster visitors that are utilizing the platform which is really successful we actually engage receive
comments shares likes with with almost 2 000 participants that are engaging and interacting
on the platform and we had 14 major city projects that were launched on the platform fix it lancaster year to date we had almost 3 500 requests for service with an average acknowledged period of 1.7 days and our average close is about 10 days to close and a request through the platform and I just wanted to share with you we just started to track foot
traffic in City Hall folks that are coming into City Hall and we have a technology that's set up there we we received from January which we launched the technology up until this morning which I got the updated numbers we twelve 12,600 guests have come into City Hall and we do about a 12% deduction for staff that are coming in and out Which is really incredible and what's really helpful is the technology that we have Can also identify peak times that also make sure that we're staffing people in the right ways
So we notice that our most peak time of service for
foot traffic on a daily like from Monday through Friday is actually Wednesday and Thursday's and lunch time and at the end of the day seem to be like really peak hours as people are coming in so we're going to continue to
analyze that technology and share that with our community planning and economic development team members that are there as well and our goals for um civic the bureau civic engagement is to expand participation really tell the story we're doing all this incredible work but we haven't been really um proactive on telling those stories so we want to increase storytelling we we're just funded through lancaster community foundation to digitize our curriculum so that
it's not only accessible to folks that are participating with us folks can download it neighborhood groups can be on there other cities can also download download and share that
curriculum so we're continuing to build what that democracy looks like and engaging our residents and continue to strengthen um fixes fix it and internal engagement we want to make sure that we're increasing folks that are utilizing fix it and logging on and reporting on the fixed platform the one also goal that's on here is the relaunch of americorps vistas with so many federal cuts we did receive federal funding that i'll share with you and so we're able to we're still on hold on hiring vistas but we are ready to go as soon as they give us the green light so the bureau of tourism and promotions so many things here but the the key thing was getting the right people in the right positions in 2025 so really excited for the team as we're building that team and we have some of those team members represented here yasmin way is our special events
manager and she's been doing a fantastic job we are in the final stages of the tourism master
plan we're coming back to you in january to release give you an overview of the tmp the tourism master plan and share with you next steps we've really increased sponsorships that we'll talk about when we start looking at revenue generation for our department and expansion and improvement events and so we've been really working on expanding our events in 2026 we're
going to establish what those priorities are with the new administration related to the tourism master plan and with our partners we're looking at the brand for the city what do we want to be known
for so we're working on that as well we'll be finalizing the welcome center renovations in the summer of 2026 we're looking at technology upgrades and we're really the biggest piece of all of this is to continue to build the sustainability of programming for special
events how are we funding and creating those funding mechanisms so that we can continue to
build this work let's see here so let me just scoot over here so our department expenses the department's proposed 2026 budget reflects a total increase of 171 604 and it's driven by investments really across all three bureaus some much less than others of course in the director's office we have an increase and it's primarily tied to expanding language services and ensuring that we're meeting the community needs like it's a really tight budget and with more projects that are coming in and more needs related to language services so we increase that and and related to
compliances there's a lot of compliances or that we have to follow also with our
mandates the Bureau of civic engagement increases reflects necessary staffing adjustments so really adjusting the work of staff with salary that compensates that and aligning team members with the correct pay structures on what they're performing on and the bureau of tourism and promotion shows the largest increase and it's
driven by staff salaries adjustments and the launch of the welcome center rebrand we had to
budget in a little bit more money for that welcome center rebrand rebrand and all of that totals 171 000 okay so um on the department revenue so i'm just going to flip back here
fast so our for our proposed 2026 general fund is one million one hundred
and fifty seven thousand dollars our department revenues proposed is one
million seventeen thousand dollars so the 2026 proposed revenue reflects
strong strategic growth across sponsorships event revenues and grants really positioning the department to continue to sustain this work and expand programming without increasing reliance on the general funds so the what we're anticipating is about 224 000 for 2026 and really that's going to be driven by sponsorships we're looking at different ways through special events to generate more revenues and so we're looking at an increase in generating revenues during our special events and we also are looking at since we're we have a portfolio for fundraising um sponsorship revenues we were looking at increasing that by 95 000. um the event revenues will grow about 27 000 and that's really due to stronger activation and anticipated attendance all these changes that we're doing to special events there's more demand there's more vendors that want to be participating in our events and with that more sponsorship so our exposure related to special events and the activation has been really great so overall grant funding increases by a hundred and two thousand dollars that's going to be directly supporting tourism civic engagement and a lot of community-centered initiatives um and as i mentioned to you before that's a really big number you know and that's something that we're really proud of i will say that there's been so many people that have been part of that the mayor has kicked it off with some of our neighborhood assistance programs that we're going to do a little bit deeper dive in the next slide tina and the advancement team has been really supportive so it's been hands all on all that to really raise some of these dollars i'm really thankful for everybody that's been involved so a little bit more detail here the grants in 2024 within um high foundation who has have supported us from the beginning lancaster county community foundation cncs which is the americorps vista program and neighborhood assistance program which is a tax credit from the state we raised 98 000 in 2025 this is what we have received and we've increased a lot of our contributions from our you know legacy partners and we have new folks that are also supporting so our 2025 where we are currently is at 372 000
and we still have these out pending we're not sure if we're going to get these in 2025 or in EARLY 2026 BUT WE STILL HAVE A HIGH FOUNDATION GRANT ASK THAT'S OUT A NEIGHBORHOOD ASSISTANCE PROGRAM APPLICATION THAT'S IN AND WITH THE STATE BUDGET HAS BEEN DELAYED WITH A REQUEST OF TWO HUNDRED THOUSAND DOLLARS AND WE ALSO HAVE A GRANT WITH THE TOURISM OFFICE AND WITH
THE BUDGET DELAYS WE HAVEN'T RECEIVED A RESPONSE OF TWO HUNDRED THOUSAND SO WE'RE REALLY EXCITED ABOUT THIS THE MAYOR AND I WERE TALKING ABOUT IT SO WE'RE KICKING OFF 2026 IN A REALLY GOOD shape so really really excited and i just wanted to highlight our special events and so our special
events increases um are due to continue growth for our special events in our portfolio which requires
a lot more resources and coordinations we might need supplies technology equipment the events remain the core part of our cities like activation drawing people downtown support
for economic the identity of the city and community pride there's so many residents that we're tracking right now that are coming from the neighborhoods to really celebrate the
city in the downtown area and the increase in sponsorship requests is primarily tied to activating bins park yule plaza and penn square and making some upgrades across all of our special
event lineup we want our goal is to continue elevating local talent but we also want to
couple it in and bring in some headline performers into special events in 2026 and we're doing this with a small and mighty team that we're very proud of so the what we're requesting from Council is an addition of one part-time person that wouldn't technically start until the end of once the Welcome Center renovations are completed in the summer and that's really to align with the hours of operations of the Welcome Center I also as I'm as I'm sharing the department staff we wouldn't be here where we are today with such excellent
hires and development of our team if it wasn't for the HR team and the support of onboarding and really supporting our team in our growth so really thankful for the HR team and Andrew that's here with us tonight he's been really awesome
and everybody it's working on that team and I just want to close that this has been a strong year for growth systems building and developing our staff and community connections and I think we're really well positioned for 2026 and our goals for the coming years focusing on strengthening service delivery upgrading our systems expanding access and fully implementing the priorities of the tourism master plan and every step supports our larger vision that we've been talking about over the last few years so just want to thank you all for the opportunity to share and continue to build this work with you so that's all that i have any questions thank you
director carasco um one question regarding the event slide uh that broke down the revenue uh
for each event uh apologize if i missed this is that based on participation in the events or is that uh dollars in sponsorships for those events so these are this is this is the slide that you're referencing okay so this is the proposed budget for each um event oh i'm sorry okay so these are the expenses for each one gotcha sorry i thought that was for revenue thank you um and one i think your team does a phenomenal job in uh punching above its weight i know everyone's really lean but you guys are everywhere um so really appreciative of that um when i look at grant support and sponsorship dollars i understand that takes a lot of activity to really support that um how are we looking to increase that knowing that um it just takes a lot of work to fundraise uh so what what activities are happening to make sure that your team is well supported with the dollars uh from grant and sponsorships yes great question thank you we work closely with the advancement team and one of the deliverables of the tourism master plan is a list of grants that we should be applying for to continue to grow work
related to the Bureau of tourism and promotion so we're diving into that a little bit more we'll be working closely with the advancement team the second part of it is with a new hire of the bureau chief of tourism and promotion one of the key backgrounds that this person has is major fundraising which we're really excited about the fundraising that we've we've were we've we've been meant we've managed to to deliver on related to sponsorships has been with I would say it's been like 10% of my time it hasn't been a lot of time
that we've invested into that we've already just started to have some preliminary conversations about what's going to be the approach and what does that look like and so it's been really excited with Kristen that's Kristen
Simon, who's our new Bureau Chief of Tourism Promotion, led all of the fundraising efforts with Penn Medicine Park.
So she came to us from the Stormers.
And so we're really thinking about
what does that portfolio look like in 2026 and how do we continue to build that? I will also say in addition to that, the opportunity to leverage the funding
that's at the state level. And so that's tourism. We were able to apply,
we received funding last year related to NAP. We tested it, and as you can see, there's $18,000. To take that in 2024 from $18,000 and then 2025 to increase it to $200,000 is really the extraordinary opportunity. So leveraging grants, sponsorship, and state funding opportunities is kind of the portfolio that we're looking at to build.
I think we have a lot of opportunity that we've been missing out on, so it'll be exciting to report out on the progress next year. Yeah, I agree. Thank you.
Thank you. Any questions or comments from council? Councilor Cleeks. Thank you, Councilor Arroyo. Thank you, Director Carrasco, for the presentation. I think that you mentioned during the presentation that the department is requesting one more
part-time person.
How many employees does the department currently have now?
We have 11. We have a total of 11 employees.
okay and uh how are resources located within the department including personal facilities and so staffing resources yep so in the director's offices um myself and zyra follow so the office of language services is within the director's office and we work very closely
in particular she she's overseeing like policy a lot of policy things so we work very closely
in the bureau of civic engagement we have four people we have one position that's not filled
that we're working to fill which is the bureau chief of civic engagement we have our engagement coordinator our engagement specialist was josh and then reception so milta is part of reception
so that's part of the civic engagement team and both of those areas are located here in city hall So the director's office and civic engagement and reception tourism and promotion we currently have five wanted to add a part-time person to that Temporarily, they're located here at City Hall with the hopes as the renovations can end
Early we might be able to move in late spring But definitely towards the summer the Bureau of tourism and promotions will be located at the Welcome Center at Penn Square
was that yes that's fine and how do you measure their performance how do you evaluate their performance within the department really great so there's a department plan and then there is a bureau plan and actually we were working on that today so we just finalized a Bureau of tourism and promotions work plan like the draft one and then each staff person has a work plan based off of that and so we have our like priorities for the bureau that have been really defined by a lot of
our planning efforts over the last year it's the same thing for the bureau civic engagement the
same thing for reception and so that's kind of what drives the work that we're doing and and really coming to you to counsel like this is what we're presenting on so our responsibility is to
come back and make sure that you know this is also um part of guiding the work for 2026. and uh So speaking of plan, is there a plan to engage on the represented communities? Yes.
Yeah, it's actually one of our core functions in everything that we're doing.
So whether we're engaging with our civic engagement programs, who is not at the table,
and what do we need to do to get them there with our language access and our communications, with our cultural events and celebrations,
we've really built a mechanism to make sure that there's representation that reflects the city of
lancaster residents thank you thank you so much director carasco no further questions thank you thank you any additional questions or comments from council councilor mitt uh thank you mr vice president thank you director carasco for the presentation um what are some ways that we can increase revenues from the special events um i really appreciated the grants the the slide about the grants and I just had a question about when we're having these events like how are some ways that we could also increase revenues from each of them oh my gosh there's so many I'm trying to get to that side I would say the I'm not sure where that side is I would say that just a couple of things is you know previously we didn't charge for vendors and so the opportunity just to even
slightly you know start charging for vendors and access to those spaces that
was one of the things that we did we have an opportunity and now with our expansion we were able to expand for more vendors so we want more vendors
more different types of vendors that are selling not only food but can we have
cultural items also represented there that's one of the things we're also one
of the areas is related to permitting for vendors that are selling alcohol and
so that's also an area the biggest opportunity is merchandising we're not selling the birch that we should during those events and so making sure that they're aligning with the theme of the event so what is celebrate look like
what's the theme in 2026 and what does the merchandise that we can sell so
there's a couple of things that we can tweak that will continue to build but the easiest thing is getting more vendors there and we have the space for that and so that's really like the easiest thing like how can we invite more people and to increase those revenues thank you and that concludes my questions any additional questions or comments from counsel from the public great thank you director Carrasco thank you so much and with that we'll move to the office of the mayor the budget before you for the office of mayor and I'm just gonna talk through this I didn't have any slides contemplates as we've discussed the rehiring of the chief of staff position it also which is the largest increase in the budget there are also increases proposed related to conferences for the incoming administration as well as travel an increase in the travel line so the the total projected budget for the mayor's office is four hundred and twenty four thousand one hundred and forty six thousand dollars with an increase of nine percent having to take any questions it's a whopping mmm eleven lines in the budget easiest presentation so far thank you sir any questions or comments from council councillor council president thank you could you talk a little bit about the
increased travel and conference budget like what types of things are do you you have in mind or would you recommend for incoming new mayor and why is that
valuable yes so a small amount but I think it's I I've recommended to mayor elect Arroyo that he attends the US Conference of mayors winter meeting in Washington DC it is something that I did annually I thought it was a little crazy that mayor gray told me to do that when you're like in office for exactly three or possibly four weeks before you're leaving and I had the benefit of staying at my cousin's house every year that I went to defray cost related hotel and so we've increased the travel line for that because while it's not that expensive to drive to DC it's really expensive to sleep there and then there's there's a mayor's innovation meeting that's also in Washington DC which is a smaller group of mayors that represent some smaller cities and I've recommended participation in that and then of course not in this budget not in this section
of the budget there is also a renewal of the membership for the Pennsylvania
Municipal League in which the future you know the mayor-elect Arroyo can decide
if they want to continue if he wants to continue to participate in that I did
a number of years but for the last two years we have not renewed our membership thank you any additional questions or comments from council from the public all right should we move on to the solicitor let's do it okay so the solicitor's office is also um a very few line items um it is It contemplates a 2026 budget of $488,546, which is an 11% decline from 2025. That is primarily due to the reduction of the assistant solicitor position in salary. There are also reductions in costs related to telephone, travel, office supplies, and minor equipment. so not a lot to talk about there it's a reduction in the overall expense projections should we move on keep on going any questions or comments from council from the public let's move on okay so this really isn't my part of the shop but I'm just gonna cover it which is City Council City Council obviously includes um costs related to each of the city councilors city controller and um and no longer city treasurer i always have to like hit pause and say yeah we're not we're not going to have a city treasurer next year um the um the total budget that is contemplated uh for um those offices and the city clerk is one hundred and seventy eight thousand eight hundred and eighty seven dollars it is a two percent increase and that two percent is largely due to the rollout let's see increased due dues expenses for the National League of Cities by two thousand dollars and I think that's about it yep Thank You Marissa Rachi and just one question there is a proposal that will be voted on I believe at the next council meeting for an increase in council salaries with that what no that doesn't take effect next year so never scratch that that's that's on you I was gonna emphasize that point though 2028 yes 2028 that is correct thank you any questions or comments from council from the public Tim Stuhlger 800 block of George Street this doesn't directly address councils budget but seems like a good point to kind of talk about this process that we are in at the moment as I keep saying you know I covered the HOME RULE PROCESS STRAIGHT THROUGH, AND THE ONE MOTIVE FOR CHANGING THE BUDGET PROCESS
WAS TO MAKE SURE COUNCIL HAD A MEANINGFUL OPPORTUNITY TO WEIGH IN ON THE BUDGET.
WE'RE SEEING THAT TAKE PLACE, EARLIER BUDGET INTRODUCTION AND TWO, THIS IS THE SECOND OF TWO BUDGET HEARINGS, BUT AGAIN, IN ORDER TO WEIGH IN MEANINGFULLY ON THE BUDGET, YOU NEED an opportunity to modify the budget, and the administration has put together a budget with lots and lots of moving parts. You obviously can't do that willy-nilly.
These hearings, you're getting a lot of good information.
My concern is whether you are having a chance to deliberate, talk amongst yourselves, and offer well-considered proposals to the administration for possible incorporation candidly as a city taxpayer i'm also hoping that you can end up passing a budget that does not draw on the reserves that seemed a lot more doable prior to this evening i would still like to see that as a goal as i said i think in the previous hearing this is about as good a years we're gonna have the economy's humming low unemployment etc a lot of headwinds coming down the pike so you know again
the budget needs as as much you know kicking the tires looking under the hood
and so forth and then as I said you know meaningful action on the part of City council so just a question to city council if you guys do have ideas about further cuts or other amendments to the budget do you have a means of doing that within the time frame of getting it
passed and then actually one follow-up to director campbell the budget that was previously presented still had the 3.6 did not have any of the the amendments that were introduced this evening
um when will an updated budget be posted and is there a chance that we could also have a brief explanation of the changes maybe not a full red line but just something the public can see i believe it is posted um and i i um this is a good moment to say that you know we the administration the council has weighed in and had wanted to see reductions in the general fund utilization and so what we presented tonight was actually a four point six million dollar shifts so that was one point if we go back to that original is like 1.3 million dollar reduction in general fund expenses with an additional 1.5 million dollar reduction in debt out of the general fund with utilization of permit fees to offset general fund and a slightly larger use of reserves now council can decide that we're not going to eliminate the entirety of that 3.6 million dollars and we're going to carry a little bit more deficit in the water fund council could also decide that we should be thinking not just about transfers from the water fund but also looking at the sewer fund which is actually healthier than the water fund there's there are a lot of different possibilities moving forward this was in response the changes were in response to council that you know we needed to back off on the general fund on utilizing reserves and so I think we did that in a significant while also addressing the transfer from the water fund just to address the specific question I do believe it is online the with the changes and we will also have these presentations online tomorrow I just I wanted to make a similar point that mayor srachi just as a member of council that because we started this process earlier generally we have a budget address and then followed almost immediately
by a first reading of the budget because we were able to spread this out and have these budget
hearings happen before that official first read while we can't deliberate not in public we could go to the administration with our concerns suggestions questions and i agree that this is a reflection of those things that have happened so for what it's worth yeah and
again some of that is not immediately obvious the same way deliberation in
this chamber is so that's helpful context thank you any additional public comment great Thank You mayor sir Archie and we'll move to our final presentation of this evening Department of Public Works director Campbell the best for last final but not the shortest yeah for that I apologize but it's good stuff I
wonder if I should have called an intermission before good evening
director Campbell thank you very very much for having me I'm Steve Campbell the director of Public Works as obviously as we move into a new administration the DPW budget always challenging presents the city with even more challenges to keep costs within reason we are proposing adjustments to and even suspension of cherished and otherwise successful programs and changes to how some necessary work gets performed despite these tough decisions i just want to reiterate that there are that there is good news there are no proposed increases to real estate taxes earned income taxes or utility rates including water sewer storm water and solid waste that's a significant achievement in a time of rising costs the city of lancaster continues to lead in the arena of environmental stewardship operational efficiency and self-performance but we must also confront serious financial pressures especially as you as has been noted in our water utility as director tina campbell has already described and some of the dpw implications of which we'll discuss in more detail here i want to take a moment to thank the entire dpw team for their hard work in developing this budget especially and please raise your hands as i say your name cindy mccormick christine volke hilditch matt messler who i believe had to leave and molly degger their leadership and dedication are critical to the services we provide every day which okay DPW is made up of approximately 210 dedicated employees with just over 1 3rd living right here in the city of Lancaster our team reflects the diversity of our community 33 percent are people of color and nearly 20 percent are women notably half of our working group leaders are women which is a point of pride and progress we continue to build upon the idea that DPW is not just one good job but is one good career we prioritize internal promotions and offer flexibility for staff to move across divisions helping us retain talent and build institutional knowledge this slide shows the organization organizational structure of DPW I was looking for a little bit more feathering of the color coding but the color coding reflects the different
enterprise fund sources blue for water yellow for wastewater pink for solid
waste and green for stormwater everything else falls under the general fund except for the box that's below construction and operations at the bottom where that's feathered out into several several different of the funds co-fund the pieces under capital construction water tnd metering etc there have been no major organizational changes this year but we remain focused on adapting our structure to meet the city's evolving needs there's a delay Public Works accounts for 12% of the city's general fund budget up slightly from 11% last year while that may seem modest it's important to note that DPW represents about 35% of the city's total workforce the services We provide clean water safe streets waste collection Storm water management and more are foundational to daily life in Lancaster These are not optional services. They are essential to public health safety and quality of life Our goal in this budget is to maintain those core services while being as efficient and cost-effective as possible possible we've worked hard to avoid service reductions even as we face rising costs and limited resources the utilities are significant elements of the city's budget the city's utilities water wastewater solid waste and storm water are funded through enterprise funds meaning they are supported by the fees paid by users not by taxes together these utilities make up a significant portion of the city's overall budget in fact the department of public works accounts for 87.2 million or 55.4 percent of the city's total budget total operating costs let's break this down the general fund portion of dpw shown in red here is 9.2 million dollars 11.3 and 11.3 increase over last year this reflects rising costs in salaries electric rates and professional services especially for vision zero and park design work the water fund shown in charcoal is at thirty eight point nine million and is our largest utility while expenses are down from last year due in part to financial restructuring mentored mentioned earlier the water utility is under significant financial pressure water rate revenue is down nearly three million dollars and costs are rising due to legal obligations infrastructure needs and energy prices we'll discuss this in more detail shortly wastewater shown in gray is at 25.5 million with a modest 3.2 percent increase this includes costs related to the consent decree and inflation driven increases in operations and energy solid waste and recycling shown in blue is at seven million also up about three percent we're still benefiting from a favorable contract but hauling and tipping fees are rising storm water is shown in light green at 6.6 million a 4.6 percent increase this reflects our continued investment in green infrastructure regulatory compliance and maintenance despite these increases we are not proposing any rate hikes in 2026. that's a major win for residents and businesses and a testament to our commitment to affordability in 2025 the department of public works made significant strides in planning technology and community engagement we launched a long-range capital budget planning tool through cleargov giving us a 22 to 32 year capital plan look ahead at infrastructure needs we began implementing city works a new work order management system that will improve how we track and respond to service requests we expanded public service announcements and educational outreach to help residents better understand the services we provide and we began shifting how we engage with the public moving from one-way communication to more collaborative community-informed processes looking ahead to 2026 our goals are ambitious but necessary we're focusing on utility financing and affordability ensuring that water and wastewater services remain financially accessible while maintaining infrastructure we're refining our capital investment strategy to prioritize the most urgent needs we're investing in workforce development recruitment retention and training to build a resilient team we're integrating technology to support data-driven decision-making and we're staying ahead of regulatory requirements especially in utilities and stormwater management in 2025 our work in the public right-of-way focused on safety accessibility and community investment we finalized designs for three southeast parks part of our commitment to equitable green space we advanced safe streets for all and vision zero initiatives including two-way street conversions and traffic signal improvements we launched the residential permit parking rpp case study program to better manage neighborhood parking and in 2026 we're taking some of the most visible and impactful challenges we're we're revolving a we're revisiting a sidewalk maintenance program to address long-standing accessibility and safety issues we'll continue to refining the RPP program and explore funding options for a citywide bike share system vision zero and safe streets for all will remain central with grant funding secured through 2029 we're investing in active transportation including the water street bike Boulevard and broad and chesapeake bike lanes and will upgrade traffic signals install red light running cameras and integrate city view permitting with the other departments to streamline processes for residents and developers in 2025 our construction and operations team delivered on several major initiatives we managed key capital projects including the welcome center bay street gardens and the new police station refurbishment we advanced climate action plan goals through led lighting upgrades and greenhouse gas reductions our launch we launched a 10-year initiative to replace lead service lines protecting public health and water quality for 2026 our focus is on strengthening our internal capacity in delivering smarter more efficient infrastructure we're addressing staffing changes by investing in recruitment retention and training we're rolling out a work order tracking system to improve transparency and accountability we'll continue the multi-phased implementation of city works improving how we manage operations we're expanding the operation center which will reduce long-term rental costs and improve service delivery we're increasing self-performance allowing our teams to take on more work in-house and and reduce costs and reliance on contractors we're also tracking tackling flood mitigation at the plum street underpass and investing in key capital improvements including the grub mansion at musser park long home at longs park pspca facility the welcome center and central market lighting upgrades in 2025 our utilities teams made significant progress on several fronts for water we secured penvest funding for critical infrastructure projects advanced our lead service line replacement initiative and continued our legal and regulatory work around pfos and pfoa contamination we also began preparing for a public utility commission puc rate case which will be essential for long-term financial sustainability on the wastewater side we submitted the judicial consent decree and began design work for an anaerobic digesters an important step toward more sustainable and cost-effective solids handling we also addressed long-standing issues at the plum street underpass looking ahead to 2026 our goals are ambitious but necessary for water as noted we were focused on affordability compliance with new pfos regulations continuing our lead line inventory and improving leak detection and backflow prevention we're also investing in staff development to ensure we have the expertise to manage these complex systems and for wastewater we'll continue implementing the consent decree roll out our new work order management system and move forward with the solids handling project these investments are about more than compliance they're about protecting public health ensuring environmental stewardship and maintaining the infrastructure that supports daily life in lancaster in 2025 our sustainability and environment team began implementing the city's first sewer separation projects on water and duke streets an important step in reducing combined sewer overflows and improving water quality we also planted over 400 street trees contributing to our long-term goal of expanding lancaster's urban tree canopy to 40 percent that's our goal and we published the 2025 climate action plan report which outlines our progress and next steps in reducing greenhouse gas emissions a presentation of which you made you will enjoy in early december for 2026 our focus is on integrating sustainability across all city departments that means exploring solar energy opportunities to reduce our reliance on increasingly expensive electricity within the context of the municipal climate action plan our plan is to implement rooftop solar on several facilities in 2026 including the operations center the water administration building and both the susquehanna and conestoga water treatment plants and the operations center expansion once installed these roofs alone should incur an annual savings of over one hundred thousand dollars starting in 2027 and garner the city a one-time federal direct pay credit of over six hundred thousand dollars in 2028 we will also be expanding our green infrastructure maintenance program to manage stormwater more effectively and cost efficiently we'll be continuing to grow our urban tree canopy we'll be improving community outreach with a focus on equity and inclusion further implementation of the municipal climate action plan and streamlining stormwater permitting to support both compliance and innovation these efforts are not just about environmental responsibility they're about long-term cost savings public health and building a more resilient city the general force the general fund portion of the dpw budget is proposed at 9.2 million an 11.3 increase over 2025. this increase reflects a mix of unavoidable cost pressures and strategic investments key drivers include rising electricity costs due to the end of our previous low rate green energy contract while we secured a competitive new rate it still represents a 65 percent increase impacting every facility especially our water and wastewater treatment plants professional services for vision zero and park design work a modest increase in vehicles including upgrades and replacements modest net new step modest net new staff but primarily some reallocation of positions and responsibilities let's look at a few bureau-specific highlights in engineering we added a right-of-way inspector to keep up with the pace of street and infrastructure work despite this we reduced professional services costs traffic a decrease here reflects a reallocation of i.t services and a reduction in street marketing marking work street maintenance increased due to staff reallocation from the water fund and the need for new vehicles motor vehicles we're adding an upfitting mechanic to install equipment and branding in-house saving an estimated 100 000 annually buildings over half of the increases due to higher electric rates we're also replacing aging vehicles and making modest increases in contract services parks we've stabilized staffing to maintain parks for recreation environmental benefits and storm water management we are also replacing older vehicles here these changes reflect our commitment to maintaining essential services while adapting to rising costs and shifting operational needs this slide outlines excuse me outline staffing changes in the general fund for 2026. while it shows an increase of nearly nine full-time equivalents it's important to understand that most of these are not new hires they are reallocations of existing staff from enterprise funds to better reflect where their work is actually being performed here are a few key highlights in engineering we've added one new position the right-of-way inspector that i mentioned earlier to help manage the growing volume of street and infrastructure work the rest of the increase is due to reassigning portions of existing staff time to the general fund in street maintenance we added one equipment operator to ensure we can keep up with essential maintenance work in motor vehicles i've mentioned the upfitting mechanic this role will allow us to install equipment and branding on city vehicles in-house saving over a hundred thousand dollars annually in labor costs in parks the increase reflects a shift in how we allocate staff who were previously funded through water or wastewater these staff are now more accurately reflected in the general fund based on where their work is actually taking place these changes are about right sizing our staff model not growing the workforce but a light aligning it with operational realities and cost efficiencies as director tina campbell has described there are significant changes in the dpw revenues for the general fund as you know the water fund has provided an annual equity transfer in the amount of up to 400 million four million dollars annually for the past eight years with the exception of two during the covet years with the financial challenge briefly outlined earlier we are endeavoring to make the water fund financially healthier in 2026 as we move forward with a water fund working group to explore ways of addressing the challenge as such this budget proposes no equity transfer from the water fund to the general fund in 2026. director tina campbell has described this in depth in her presentation this evening eliminating this transfer will support the water fund but will cause the shifts that she presented in the general fund a consequence of the structural requirement of the water bureau enterprise fund transfer has been that the water utility operates extremely efficiently it which it absolutely does in order to break even fee revenues for public works are comprised of three main areas right-of-way permit fees city property rental and vehicle repairs that we perform for a few outside municipal entities this year those revenues are revenues are down slightly but still healthy overall the downturn is in two of these areas the right-of-way permit fees and rent of city property enterprise fund cost reimbursements pay for direct services that they use from the general fund this includes things like office space electric and other utility payments and services provided this year those reimbursements are up by over four hundred thousand dollars as this includes updated technology needs general increases in staff and benefit costs that we see across the organization and general increases that we are seeing in costs for services such as our audit and other required obligations in short while the revenue picture is shifting we're making thoughtful adjustments to ensure long-term sustainability without burdening taxpayers or ratepayers let's take a quick closer look at the financial picture for our two largest enterprise funds water and wastewater starting with water revenue is down seven percent largely due to reduced water usage this is part of a national trend towards conservation driven by more efficient appliances and locally by our recent drought and a good level of conservation compliance by the public while this is good for the environment and for rate payer bills it creates a challenge for a utility that has high fixed costs expenses are also down by about nine percent primarily because we've eliminated the four million dollar equity transfer to the general fund this gives the water fund some breathing room as we work toward a more sustainable financial model however costs continue to rise in key areas legal and professional fees services related to pfos and lead service lines energy costs which are up 732 thousand dollars for the conestoga and susquehanna plants alone due to the new energy contract and regulatory compliance we've added one chief operator to both to support both water plants but overall staffing is down due to attrition and reallocations for wastewater revenue is down slightly which is expected given the parallel drop in water usage expenses are up about three percent driven by inflation and specific needs like legal services for the consent decree and increased energy and chemical costs we've added two positions a labor supervisor for our pumping stations and a plant supervisor to support the wastewater plant manager who currently oversees 17 17 direct reports of far more than is sustainable these changes reflect our commitment to maintaining high quality utility services while managing costs and preparing for future regulatory and infrastructure demands let's now take a quick look at solid waste and recycling and stormwater enterprise funds starting with solid waste revenue is essentially flat up just one tenth of one percent this stability is due to the 10 rate increase implement implemented last year which continues to carry us through 2026. expenses however are up 3.1 percent this is driven by rising hauling and tipping fees which are outside of our contractual control and continue to increase across the industry we're also investing in professional services to assess whether solid waste so close to operating without a deficit could become a revenue generating operation in the future additionally 230 000 in administrative and i.t costs have been reallocated to better reflect actual service delivery in support of the highly successful fix-it program among other things some good news is that with the ex expansion of the operation center at the the conestoga water treatment plant we anticipate eliminating the 60 000 annual rental we currently pay to boral industries starting as early as 2027. now for stormwater revenue is down 2.9 percent as we are not proposing any fee increases at this time expenses are up 4.6 reflecting our commitment to maintaining and improving green infrastructure complying with stormwater regulations and implementing the municipal climate action plan key investments include hiring an equipment operator to support green infrastructure maintenance increased professional services for design and compliance and a vehicle upgrade to support the trees for people program these investments are essentially are essential to keep stormwater management cost effective and environmentally responsible especially as we work to reduce combine sewer overflows and improve water quality city-wide just about finished this slide summarizes staffing changes across the enterprise funds overall there's a net reduction of 2.47 full-time equivalents but again this is largely due to reallocations not layoffs or service reductions in water to reiterate staffing is down by 1.82 ftes while we are adding one chief operator to support both water plants several positions have been reallocated to the general fund or better reflect where the work is being done in wastewater staffing is up slightly by almost one half an fte this includes two important additions the labor the labor supervisor maintenance foreman for our sewer pumping stations and the wastewater plant supervisor to support the plant manager who currently oversees an unsustainable number of direct reports in solid waste the small decrease is purely a reallocation of existing staff and in stormwater we've added an equipment operator to support green infrastructure maintenance but reallocated other positions to the general fund resulting in a net decrease of 1.04 ftes these staffing adjustments are about continuing to align our workforce with operational needs and funding sources ensuring we're using public dollars efficiently while maintaining the high level of service our residents expect thank you for your time and attention this evening as we've seen the 2026 dpw budget reflects a careful balance between fiscal responsibility and our commitment to delivering essential services we are navigating rising costs aging infrastructure and regulatory demands while still avoiding tax or rate increases for residences and businesses our approach is grounded in transparency equity and long-term sustainability whether it's maintaining safe streets delivering clean water managing storm water or investing in green infrastructure every decision in this budget is aimed at protecting public health supporting our neighborhoods and building a stronger lancaster we look forward to working with city council our community partners and you the residents and rate payers to continue developing high quality public services in 2026 and beyond my division heads and i are now happy
to take any questions you may have thank you director campbell um for the presentation and
for also running a tight ship i know it's uh very impressive on what you're able to do um here in the city with so many moving pieces uh just one question regarding the drop in water consumption um my understanding is that we're looking at trends uh and i'm not sure if that work has been completed or not but uh do we continue to foresee in the future that we will see a drop in water consumption over the years and is that cause for concern it is a very good question um i believe that we will continue to see a modest but decrease but not at the level that we've seen recently a huge part of the decrease that we've seen recently was related to the to the drought and the fact that many in our community were very compliant and very conscious conscious and conscientious in dealing with water conservation measures i don't know chris if there's anything else you wanted to be able to add to something like that
Thank you any questions or comments from council council president. Thank you. I think I have three
fairly quick
Questions how often do we renegotiate our energy costs and did they are they only? Under contract for our utility services, or is that in general? It's a good question the the last We brought the contract that ends this fall on I believe in 2019 Okay, and that was part of them that was a negotiated effort to be compliant with the municipal climate action plan It's a hundred percent constant hundred percent renewable energy Sources, etc. And we were able to extend that contract by one or two years to keep the lower rates however that we could not extend it beyond this current year and therefore we need to do a competitive bidding for for MCAP, Municipal Climate Action Plan compliant energy sources, initially we were fearful that the rates had gone up as much to about $0.11 per kilowatt hour, where what the original contract had, as Tina's presentation showed, the original contract had rates of 5.4%, and we were able to get a negotiated Rate of eight point eight cents per kilowatt hour in this new contract much less than the eleven cents But still a sixty five percent increase sixty or sixty five percent increase Thank you and earlier in the presentation. You mentioned, you know the reallocation of staff
To move them in alignment with their duties. This is kind of a strange question
You mentioned that there was part positions in the water fund Is that is that I hear that correct? Yes, because parks people generally so the simple version is that we often had parks people do the clearance of grub and
Lawn work around the utilities. Uh-huh partly for security and partly for just general cleanliness
Many of the staff that are on those sites now can do that work from their positions as laborers in in the in the water plants or the wastewater plant themselves and therefore we don't need to re have the parks staff do that work that park staff could go back to doing parks and stormwater management if you will that makes sense my last one you mentioned the possibility of looking at the solid waste and recycling budget because it's relatively flat as a potential revenue source in the future is that something that's just we were looking at that because we see that it's flat is that reality and how many years away do you suspect that that might be if you had a crystal ball which you don't oh I do have a crystal ball how you're so good so I I'm very hopeful but the reality is such that we're confined by the space that we currently occupy it's not large enough for to be able to expand to be as profit-making as we would like we know that the public loves to use our recycling center they they'll line up around the block during certain days of the week to make sure that they can use our Center the way we the way we anticipate but we don't have enough space for expansion we had hoped that that when by looking at alternate locations for the operation center expansion, we'd be able to find a site that would be large enough for an expanded solid waste management service. We have not been successful in that regard, but we do believe the trends are such that we can, with greater capacity, make it a revenue producing opportunity. this moment we don't have this the the space or the funds to be able to make that kind of an investment but i'm hopeful that that's something that can be in a longer term management plan thank you thank you council president council harsh thank you council vice president thank you director camel um just to kind of i just wanted to piggyback off that last question um
because my understanding yeah is that we you know have sale of those recyclable materials Can you just remind me what the expansion and the capacity is like are we gonna have double or triple?
and then or or you know, however percent increase and do we expect like a pretty
Corollary relationship between the expansion like if we get double the op space we get double the recycle material Revenue or not necessarily not necessarily. Those are very good questions
That's part of what we're trying to trying to study it goes to not only what the current market is for recyclable recycling and recyclables, but what the surrounding Environment is as well. Laksam is very successful in how it does recycling work and the the trends are even though there's been a dipped trend in recyclables the our recyclable weight and volume has generally continued to go up in spite of those trends we have no way yet of monetizing that that's part of what the nature of studying and being able to look at the opportunities are but I can almost assure you that it's not a direct line increase it would be an investment if we were the value would have been if we were already going to be replacing and making that site larger or the recycling capability larger to what extent do you add certain kinds of capacity for what kinds of materials how do you market it differently how do you bring people on into the site etc and so those are the things we want to be aware of as in the future we start to look for a new site
thank you that's helpful and then my other question kind of relates to an earlier question I had about like cost savings and I know we're very much at the outset of this so I understand if there's not many much in the way of answers right now I am curious though about the expansion of solar facilities for city property and just how that works as far as seeing either cost savings or are there going to be like I guess some kind of energy credit that comes back to the city how does that result or how would that result in cost savings for the city in the long run if you have some time councillor Hirsch I
think Molly Dager could walk you through a PowerPoint presentation that she prepared that could show the buildings that are being contemplated the financing structure the tax credits that would be applied and the savings over time and just in the interest of time tonight if you're good with that I think
that sounds great Molly can share that with you it sounds excellent thank you
councilman Thank You mr. vice president Thank You director Campbell this presentation was very helpful and I know this question was probably exhausted many times but if we were to bring the water fund equity transfer to two million like it was in 2023 and 2024 what implications would that have on the water fund on the water fund alone it would allow us most likely to be in a healthier situation but i can't say that we'd be in the same surplus situation that we had episodically for those two years the costs have gone up significantly when when when uh when director campbell mentioned that we're still going into 2026 with a 2 million dollar deficit in water 750 000 of that is the electrical increase for the new contract that's that's something that would not have been anticipated um at that extraordinary level so there's no guarantee of what it would have been but it would have been a healthier cash flow and a healthier financial position for us to continue to move forward in i do believe that the way we're we're framing it which is to not have that transfer this coming year and take this time through a working group etc to look at the opportunities the options and the ways that the the water transfer as well as other cost implications might be affected will be very very useful we have information from pfm that was cited in in tina's presentation they're the the financial accounting municipal accounting organization that had done some of the preliminary study work for us a couple of years ago they would be able to to give us more input and there's a lot of information about how many of these utilities are morphing in how they manage themselves financially thank you because I mean I do want to state that I do have some anxieties about eliminating the transfers in the in the long run given you know it would it would significantly change the projections that we've seen previously so I just you
know I know that we're looking to do this working group of what would be some of the strategies maybe like a performance based transfer like was mentioned earlier but what would be some of the pathways to once again have that
transfer to the general fund I think that that is going to be a great conversation to kick off the water fund task force with and I'm hesitant start to go down that path at this particular moment it is a conversation there are some recommendations in the PFM study that need to be revisited and I and I think these are conversations that I'm actually having with mayor-elect Arroyo to begin to frame that out and for him to be able to consider who he would want to be part of that task force if that is the direction that he wants to go in there's some structural things there are some financial things there's a combination of of there's some calculation in terms of risk of not meeting some of the standards at the pace in which they are required so the lead line replacement went from 25 25 years to 10 and so if if that were to be extended back to 25 years that has a huge impact on the capital costs and the borrowing for for the water fund so there's a variety of variables that need to be taken into account and I think that there's some more setup that needs
to be happening happen for council and a particular this particular working group
to be able to really understand that and and understand all of the levers that
could be pushed or pulled to get the water fund to a place where those
transfers are happening I would say just to reiterate what director Tina Campbell mentioned council should consider this as an annual one-time thing for this moment to be able to get to this next piece of work does that help counselor yes I know I'm kind of kicking it forward but it's it's there's a lot to unpack there thank you then just my final question is in regards to the debt
of the water fund do we have any more capacity for any more borrowing what would the budgetary
impact look like to kind of help make the water fund more healthy and also keep the general fund healthy i think that's again a tina issue again with lots of variables um so you're asking if there's more capacity to borrow at this point um there there is um we in the in the capital plan
that was approved the five-year capital plan it actually shows about 87 million in unfunded projects at this point so that either needs to be funded through borrowing or or grant funding
which you know we would work on as well um i i would say you know as as part of the capital planning process we actually um there there is um without getting into too many details there is there is a cap to what we can borrow i mean that legitimately like a legal cap to what we can borrow and we needed to cut out some of the planned projects in that five years because of that cap so that 87 million is still within that cap but it's it would put us really tight thank you and i appreciate all the work that your department's doing well i have both campbell's at the at the desk um kind of kind of piggybacking off of the uh question with the transfer uh the four million dollar transfer are we thinking this correctly um we're paying for it in some way so if it's getting transferred um to the general fund that then creates a necessity for potential rate increases on city only city uh rate pairs um if we don't transfer it over then we just have to
balance the general fund that so is that a good way to think of it that city city residents are
paying for it in some way just whether it's tax dollars or water rates correct yeah because like we mentioned earlier the PUC doesn't count that as an expense and so it needs to come from city residents in some way yeah so I think that's good for council to consider because I think you know we're thinking of it as trying to balance the general fund but we'll just end up increasing tax rates eventually if it in order to balance the waterfront budget potentially. Thank you. Any councillor colleagues? Thank you. Thank you. Thank you director Campbell for the presentation. I don't know if I missed that part of the budget. I don't know if you mentioned that. Are there any provisions made within the budget to address unexpected events or emergencies like severe water events or natural disasters are there any provisions for that in the budget that is our reserve fund counselor colleagues for when bad
things happen that aren't budgeted thank you and that's why it's important for us
to maintain a healthy reserve amount okay anyways you've been whistling past
the graveyard for a while i've talked i spoke two or three years ago about some changes that
we had made in terms of the long-term i'm sorry the large diameter uh pipe that has to be replaced because it was way beyond its useful life where we've made such huge progress in that regard but we're we're very fortunate that we've got a team of people who are looking very closely at the conditions of the buildings that we now have facility condition assessments
that manage what our expectations are but we do not have sufficient reserves
to take on a key emergency without having to refinance or or borrow extensively to do that and are there any changes in funding sources or additional with your streams for the department comparing to the previous year's budget in areas outside of the utilities we have where have hope fingers crossed about continued grant work as an example the we we were granted a million dollars to do tree tree work and that was not clawed back by the administration we've got an additional five hundred thousand dollars to do I forget what it was it was also related to green infrastructure and that was not clawed back so at this moment knock on wood the grants position for the city in the areas where we are already excelling is not bad it's not good but it's not bad but we're looking grants as opportunities we're looking at being able to to have coalitions with other organizations like clean water partners the alliance for the chesapeake bay etc to identify and leverage opportunities thank you thank you thank you any additional questions or comments from council from the public yeah uh one comment one question um appreciate council digging in on the THE DETAILS OF THE PROPOSED WATER EQUITY FUND TRANSFER. ONE THING I WOULD POINT OUT IS THE CLASS OF IN-CITY RATEPAYERS AND THE CLASS OF IN-CITY
TAXPAYERS, THOSE ARE DIFFERENT CLASSES.
IN PARTICULAR, WATER RATES FALL ON THE UNTAXABLE PROPERTIES THAT DO NOT PAY PROPERTY TAXES AND THOSE INCLUDE SOME PRETTY AFFLUENT ENTITIES INCLUDING F&M AND LGH, ALSO INCLUDES COUNTY government i don't know you know how you could model the incidence of doing a partial transfer leaving something in here leaving something out there but again the the incidences are are different if property taxpayers are bearing the burden versus if rate payers are bearing the burden so that's my comment my question would be to director campbell in this case department of public works director campbell i noticed that it looks like most of the enterprise funds are at or are either really close to breaking even or are even running a slight deficit that suggests that
even though we are not looking at rate increases this year it seems like there's a prospect for weight increases the following year wondering if you could comment that and if you comment on that
and even talk specifically fund by fund um i think to a certain extent you're you're correct that we're we're very close to what the costs are in past years we had relatively modest increases inflation among other things has caught up with some of the with some of those funds and we need to embrace almost as a paradigm shift the idea of what can we do more on our own this is why we've we've we're doing some investment in staffing and in being able to do more self-performance so that we have more control over the means of production and the work that has to get done it means would that we would be more light on our feet if you will to make harder decisions in the future rather than be forced or stuck with a contract uh to to do to do certain work in a particular way um i am like i say i am hopeful about the the solid waste fund um but the others in large part have been keeping up with with with in with inflation and we are wanting to continue to invest in the design dollars so that we can get more work permitted and in the ground which makes us eligible whether it's in water wastewater or stormwater for the pen vest loans so I think part of it is how we position ourselves to get the work done yeah and again appreciate the
complexity the difficulty the the high cost of building anything in 2025 and and forward I guess my follow-up comment would be if it is likely that we're
looking at tax or enough tax it at rate increases in 2027 in my view that makes
it all the more important to try to set the general fund up to be as strong as
possible so that we're if we have to do the rate increases we don't also have to do uh either an eit or a real estate tax increase that's all um regarding solid waste and recycling i recall that it was maybe three years ago uh there was a campaign to uh try to get people to be a little bit more disciplined about what they put in the recycling bin uh uh and i guess that worked a little but i can tell you that walking around on a on a trash collection morning and looking in people's recycling bin there's all kinds of stuff in there than those that has there ever been any consideration of imposing a fine on on people who uh who don't follow the rules uh similar to uh you know the way we do with street cleaning i think that's a very good question we're always open to options for increased revenue what that fine would likely trigger for us is additional staffing and additional costs for implementation of of enforcement and i think we're not yet ready to to take that on in the way that would be most successful but we're you're right the pro the programs that we've had in the past were very successful and then without being able to monitor them or stay on top of them or with attrition with staff attrition we lost the ability to to enforce at the level that would make them useful again i think part of what we would be looking at with the with the study that we're contemplating is what would be necessary to make enforcement and those kinds of regulations revenue producing again any additional public comment
great Thank You director Campbell and with that council president I'll
conclude the Finance Committee thank you very much councillors we have concluded our agenda for this evening and I'll hear a motion to adjourn motion to adjourn second all in favor aye we're adjourned thank you